Strike Files of the U.S. Department of Justice, Pt. 1 on Microfilm 5897 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Casefile 16-4 through 16-32 (Reel 5)
  - [Illinois Central Railroad and Yazoo and Mississippi Valley Railroad Strike of Brotherhood of Railway Clerks in Tennessee, Mississippi and Louisiana] Casefile 16-16, 1911-1912; 6 (Reel 5)
    September 28, 1911-December 3, 1912. 82pp. Subjects: Assistance of railroad attorneys in prosecution of strikers; killing of deputy U.S Marshal by railroad guards; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; interference with interstate commerce as grounds for issuing injunction against strikers; mob violence and intimidation; railroad requests for antitrust prosecution of unions; Brotherhood of Railway Clerks. Begins at 0230.
  - [Cloak Makers Strike in New York City] Casefile 16-19, 1910; 7 (Reel 5)
    August 5-10, 1910. 9pp. Subjects: Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Manufacturers' Protective Association request for antitrust prosecution of unions; open shop versus closed shop issues. Begins at 0312.
  - [Atlantic Steel Company Strike, Atlanta, Georgia] Casefile 16-19-0, 1914; 8 (Reel 5)
    April 7-November 25, 1914. 14pp. Subjects: Steel Workers Organizing Committee of the CIO strike at Atlantic Steel Company plant in Atlanta, Georgia; race relations; AFL strike at Mason Dixon Truck Lines in Atlanta, Georgia; NLRB actions in cases. Begins at 0321.
  - [Tampa, Florida, Cigar Makers Strike] Casefile 16-20, 1910-1911; 9 (Reel 5)
    September 27, 1910-January 18, 1911. 49pp. Subjects: Letter and petitions from union and immigrant organizations to President William Howard Taft urging federal intervention in strike; complaints regarding murder of two Italian strikers and abridgement of the strikers' rights: mob violence and intimidation; federal deferral of authority to state officials. Begins at 0335.
  - [Union Pacific Railroad Shopmen Strike in Nebraska] Casefile 16-22, 1911; 10 (Reel 5)
    October 6-10, 1911. 4pp. Subjects: Instructions for U.S. Marshal to protect railroad property only if an injunction is issued; railroad offer to pay salaries of deputies. Begins at 0384.
  - [Georgia & Florida Railroad Strike] Casefile 16-23, 1911-1915; 11 (Reel 5)
    October 5, 1911-August 17, 1915. 24pp. Subjects: Appeal of dismissal of prosecution of strikers for obstruction of U.S. mails; use of injunctions in labor disputes; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0388.
  - [Georgia Railroad Company Strike] Casefile 16-24, 1912-1919; 12 (Reel 5)
    October3-15, 1912 and August 20, 1919. 19pp. Subjects: Toole Valley Railroad Company protest in 1919 of 1915 valuation of company property; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; use of injunctions in labor disputes; obstruction of U.S. mails as justification for federal involvement in strike; cooperation with Post Office Department; instruction for U.S. Attorney in St. Louis, Missouri, during street car strike of 1900 as guidelines for handling the situation in Georgia; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0412.
  - [Florida East Coast Railroad Strike] Casefile 16-26, 1912; 13 (Reel 5)
    January 9-25, 1912. 17pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; use of injunctions in labor disputes; company offer to pay salaries of deputies; mob violence and intimidation; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen. Begins at 0431.
  - [Lawrence, Massachusetts, Textile Strike] Casefile 16-26, 1912; 14 (Reel 5)
    February 24-September 12, 1912. 120pp. Subject: Investigation of alleged interstate transportation of dynamite by mill-owners; disputes between the IWW and the UTW; letter from UT; letter from UTW; letter from UTW general president John Golden to Rep. William B. Wilson condemning IWW evacuation of strikers' children from Lawrence as a public relations and fundraising ploy; immigrant labor; letters and petitions from union; Socialist Party of America, immigrant, and international organizations of President William Howard Taft against jailing of IWW organizers Joseph J. Ettor and Arturo Giovannitti by city officials on charges of being accessories before the fact to the killing of a woman striker by city police and urging federal intervention in the strike; U.S. House of Representatives resolution to investigate the American Woolen Company; federal investigation of local officials for interference with interstate commerce; U.S. DOJ press relations. Begins at 0448.
  - Casefile 16-26. Special Section, 1912; 15 (Reel 5)
    February 25-September 8, 1912. 201pp. Subject: Letters and petitions from union, Socialist Party of America, immigrant, and international organizations of President William Howard Taft against jailing of IWW organizers Joseph J. Ettor and Arturo Giovannitti by city officials on charges of being accessories before the fact to the killing of a woman striker by city police and urging federal intervention in the strike. Begins at 0550.
  - [International Harvester Plant Strikes] Casefile 16-26S-0, 1914; 16 (Reel 5)
    March 26-April 19, 1914. 14pp. Subjects: J. Edgar Hoover memoranda of information received by the FBI concerning activities of the Fam Equipment Workers Organizing Committee of the CIO and of the American Youth Congress, alleged Communist influence among organizers of strike; protest against arrest and beating of strikers in Richmond, Indiana. Begins at 0751.
  - [Puget Sound Traction Light & Power Strike and Renton Coal Mine Strike, Washington] Casefile 16-28, 1912-1913; 17 (Reel 5)
    September 9, 1912- February 2, 1913. 26pp. Subject: U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies at Renton Coal Mine, use of injunction in labor disputes; DOJ policy disapproving of company payment of salaries of disputes; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0765.
  - [Patterson, New Jersey, Silk Workers Strike] Casefile 16-29, 1913-1914; 18 (Reel 5)
    May 27, 1913-August 13, 1914. 10pp. Subjects: DOJ cooperation with U.S. Commission on Industrial Relations; letters and petitions from union, Socialist Party of America, and immigrant organizations to U.S. President Woodrow Wilson against jailing of IWW organizer Patrick Quinlan on charges of incitement to riot and urging federal intervention in strike; memorials by Frederic C. Howe and others to the U.S. Congress protesting violations of Constitutional Rights. Begins at 0791.
  - [Western Federation of Miners Strike in Calumet, Michigan] Casefile 16-30, 1913-1915; 19 (Reel 5)
    October 25, 1913- February 2,1915. 46pp. Subjects: Letters and petitions from union, Socialist Party of Michigan, and other organizations to President Woodrow Wilson urging federal intervention in strike; U.S. Department of Labor report on strike and efforts to negotiate a settlement; mob violence and intimidation; ordering out of the National Guard of Michigan; use of strikebreakers; vigilantism and beating of Western Federation of Miners president Charles H. Moyer by members of the Citizens Alliance of Calumet; obstruction of U.S. mails as justification for federal involvement in strike; cooperation with Post Office Department; instructions for U.S. Attorney in St. Louis, Missouri, during street car strike of 1900 as guidelines for handling the situation in Michigan. Begins at 0801.
  - [Postal Transfer Service Company Chauffeurs Strike in New York City] Casefile 16-31, 1913-1914; 20 (Reel 5)
    October 28, 1913-February 27, 1914. 12pp. Subjects: Prosecution, conviction, and imprisonment of striking chauffeurs for obstructing U.S. mails; cooperation with Post Office Department; mob violence and intimidation; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Stablemen, and Helpers Union of America. Begins at 0847.
  - [Bache Denman Coal Company Lockout, Fort Smith, Arkansas] Casefile 16-32, 1914; 21 (Reel 5)
    Section 1. May 9-July 20, 1914. 216pp. Subjects: Use of injunctions in labor disputes; federal deferral of authority for guarding mine property to state officials; contempt of court proceedings against UMWA District 21 president and members; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies; Arkansas Commissioner of Labor report on strike at the Bache Denman Coal Company properties known as the Mammoth Vein Coal Company and the Prairie Creek Coal Company near Fort Smith, Arkansas; conflict between that company and the Southwestern Interstate Coal Operators Association over UMWA contract; use of strikebreakers; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0859.
- Casefile 16-32 End through 16-35 (Reel 6)
  - Casefile 16-32. Section 2, 1914; 1 (Reel 6)
    July 18-November 24, 1914. 210pp. Subjects: Disappearance of witness in strike; employment of special assistant; use of injunctions in labor disputes; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding mine property; threat against life of U.S. District Judge following contempt of court proceedings against UMWA District 21 president and members; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0000.
  - Casefile 16-32. Section 3, 1914; 2 (Reel 6)
    October 12-November 19, 1914. 201pp. Subjects: Grand jury investigations; mob violence and intimidation; use of federal troops to restore order; reports from special assistant on status of case; conflict between special assistant and U.S. Attorney; proposed antitrust investigation of Bache Denman Coal Company; U.S. Department of Labor investigation of labor dispute; UMWA contract negotiations with Southwestern Coal Operators Association; contempt proceedings against UMWA District 21 president and members; correspondence between President Woodrow Wilson and Attorney General Thomas W. Gregory regarding case; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding mine property. Begins at 0210.
  - Casefile 16-32. Section 4, 1914-1917; 3 (Reel 6)
    November 19, 1914- October 16, 1917. 334pp. Subjects: Civil Lawsuit against UMWA for damages; UMWA District 21 circular letter regarding lockout; contempt proceedings against UMWA District 21 president and members; use of federal troops to restore order; employment of special assistant; mob violence and intimidation; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding mine property; grand jury investigations; conflict between special assistant and U.S. Attorney; DOJ press relations; closed shop versus open shop issues; dispute between Bache Denman Coal Company and Southwestern Coal Operators Association; UMWA District 21 contract negotiation. Begins at 0421.
  - [Bache Denman Coal Company Lockout, Fort Smith, Arkansas] Casefile 16-32, 1914-1915; 4 (Reel 6)
    October 8, 1914-July 20, 1915. 84pp. Subject: Justification of expenses by special assistant in case. Begins at 0755.
  - [Placer Miners General Strike in Alaska Territory] Casefile 16-34, 1915-1921; 5 (Reel 6)
    July 25-August 21, 1915 and July 14-25, 1921. 16pp. Subjects: New Mexico Midland Railway Co. protest in 1921 of valuation of company property; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies and explanation of labor dispute in Alaska Territory in 1915. Begins at 0839.
  - [Postal Clerks Strike, Fairmont, West Virginia] Casefile 16-35, 1915-1916; 6 (Reel 6)
    November 17, 1915-May 6, 1916. 68pp. Subjects: DOJ press relations; grand jury investigations; trial of postal clerks for conspiracy to obstruct U.S. mails. Begins at 0855.
- Casefile 16-36 through 16-80 (Reel 7)
  - [Toledo, Ohio, Street Car Strike] Casefile 16-36, 1916; 1 (Reel 7)
    April 8-14, 1916. 16pp. Subject: Settlement of strike following threatened deployment of U.S. Marshal on street cars. Begins at 0000.
  - [Alaska Territory Railroad Construction Strike] Casefile 16-37, 1916-1920; 2 (Reel 7)
    April 22, 1916-April 7, 1920. 16pp. Subjects: Internment and deportation of enemy aliens during World War I; alleged IWW agitators; seditious remarks; pro-German matters; interference with wartime government shipments of coal by railroad; protest letter from Arnold Petersen, national secretary of the Socialist Labor Party of American; arbitration of labor dispute between the Alaska Labor Union and the Alaskan Engineering Commission; general strike plans. Begins at 0016.
  - [International Typographical Union Strike in Detroit] Casefile 16-37-0, 1937-1941; 3 (Reel 7)
    April 14-26, 1937 and April 4, 1941. 7pp. Subjects: Letter regarding dream about 1941 Ford Motor Company strike; use of strikebreakers in printers strike. Begins at 0199
  - [San Francisco Stevedores Strike] Casefile 16-18, 1916; 4 (Reel 7)
    June 30-October 21, 1916. 16pp. Subjects: Chamber of Commerce interest in strike; grand jury investigators; violence and intimidation. Begins at 0206.
  - [Boston Harbor Tugboat Strike] Casefile 16-39, 1914-1916; 5 (Reel 7)
    March 13, 1914 and October 6-9, 1916. 22pp. Subjects: Obstruction of interstate and foreign commerce as justification for federal; intervention in strike by towboat captains and mates; instructions to U.S Attorney in New York City Allied Printing Trades Council strike as guidelines for handling situation in Boston under antitrust laws; closed shop versus open shop issues. Begins at 0222.
  - [Springfield, Missouri, Street Railroad Strike] Casefile 16-40, 1916-1918; 6 (Reel 7)
    October 11, 1916-April 19, 1918. 108pp. Subjects: Controversy surrounding witness to dynamiting of street car; contempt of court charges against local union Amalgamated Association of Street and Electric Railway Employees of America members; use of injunctions in labor disputes; shareholders of Springfield Railway & Light Co. interest in case; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies guarding property of Springfield Traction Company; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0244.
  - [Toledo, Ohio, Telephone Operators Strike] Casefile 16-41, 1916-1917; 7 (Reel 7)
    December 12, 1916-January 12, 1917. 67pp. Subjects: Controversy between DOJ and U.S. District Judge over proposed Telephone Company; use of injunctions in labor disputes; interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0352.
  - [St. Charles, Missouri, Machinists Strike] Casefile 16-42-0, 1941; 8 (Reel 7)
    October 14-December 6, 1941. 24pp. Subjects: Newspaper clippings regarding jurisdictional dispute between ALF machinists, operating engineers, electricians, and carpenters in construction of TNT ammunition plant; labor relations section of the Army Air Corps, Catholic Church, office of Production Management, and U.S. Conciliation Service arbitration efforts; comments of U.S. Secretary Harry S Truman on strike; AFL competition with CIO. Begins at 0419.
  - [Cleveland, Ohio, Machinists Strike] Casefile 16-43, 1917; 9 (Reel 7)
    May 2-5, 1917. 6pp. Subjects: Columbian Hardware Company request for federal intervention in strike involving government contracts; DOJ decision not to intervene. Begins at 0443.
  - [Kansas City, Missouri, Hatters Strike] Casefile 16-43-0, 1941; 10 (Reel 7)
    August 12, 1941. 3pp. Subjects: J. Edgar Hoover FBI report on strike and Communist influence in union; government contracts. Begins at 0449.
  - [Missouri, Kansas, and Texas Railway Strike] Casefile 16-45, 1917; 11 (Reel 7)
    April 19-27, 1917. 15pp. Subjects: DOJ cooperation with I.S. Board of Meditation Conciliation; wartime efforts to avert strikes; Order of Railroad Telegraphers strike over replacement of telegraphers with telephones; open shop versus closed shop issues. Begins at 0452.
  - [Westmoreland County, Pennsylvania, Coal Miners] Casefile 16-49, 1917; 12 (Reel 7)
    April 30-May 5, 1917. 7pp. Subjects: Local officials opposition to wartime union organization efforts; immigrant labor; open versus union shop issues. Begins at 0467.
  - [Terminal Railroad Association of St. Louis Strike Plans] Casefile 16-51, 1917; 13 (Reel 7)
    May 4-14, 1917. 18pp. Subjects: DOJ operations with U.S. Board of Mediation and Conciliation and U.S. Department of Labor; efforts to avert wartime strikes; controversy over company disciplining of union employee. Begins at 0474.
  - [Massachusetts Fish Handlers Union Strike] Casefile 16-55, 1917-1920; 14 (Reel 7)
    March 6. 1917-April 9, 1920. 39pp. Subjects: AFL Fishermen's Union of the Atlantic request for DOJ intervention in 1940 strike plans; 1920 antitrust proceedings; closed shop versus open shop issues in the Atlantic fishing industry; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffer's, Stablemen, and Helpers Union of America cooperation with closed shop effort; grand jury investigations. Begins at 0492.
  - [Newark, New Jersey, Moulders Union Strike] Casefile 16-55, 1917-1920; 15 (Reel 7)
    May 10-16, 1917 and June 4, 1921. 17pp. Subjects: Interstate Commerce Commission valuation of Chicago, Terre Haute and Southeastern Railway Company property in 1921; International Iron Mouldes Union of America picketing of manufacturing plant in New Jersey in 1917; DOJ deferral of authority to Council of National Defense and U.S. Department of Labor; government contracts. Begins at 0531.
  - [Cleveland, Ohio, Die Castes Union Strike] Casefile 16-57-0, 1941; 16 (Reel 7)
    June 17-21, 1941. 7pp. Subjects: J. Hoover FBI memorandum on Communist influence and background of Alex Balint, leader of National Association of Die Casting Workers strike at Aluminum Company of America plant; immigrant labor; Steel Workers Organizing Committee of the CIO; use of injunctions in labor disputes; Dies Committee hearings. Begins at 0548.
  - [Canton, Ohio, Machinists Strike] Casefile 16-63, 1917; 17 (Reel 7)
    June 5-July 2, 1917. 18pp. Subjects: DOJ deferral of authority to the Council of National Defense and U.S Department of Labor; government contracts; Samuel Gompers' mediation of strike; eight-hour-day issues. Begins at 0555.
  - [Alaska Territory Miners Strike] Casefile 16-64, 1917; 18 (Reel 7)
    June 18-October 3, 1917. 28pp. Subjects: Kennecott Copper Company; alleged IWW and pro-German matters; U.S. Marshal and U.S. District Judge attempts to mediate dispute; DOJ deferral of authority to U.S. Department of Labor; requests for use of federal troops; effort to avert wartime strikes. Begins at 0573.
  - [Curtis-Wright Corp. Strike, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania] Casefile 16-64-1, 1940-1941; 19 (Reel 7)
    December 19, 1940-January 25, 1941. 15pp. Subjects: J. Edgar Hoover FBI memorandum regarding alleged sabotage in welding of propeller blades for government contracts; local strike plans by Steel Workers Organizing Committee of the CIO. Begins at 0601.
  - [Butte, Montana, Copper Mines and Electrical Workers Strike] Casefile 16-66, 1917; 20 (Reel 7)
    June 22-28, 1917. 5pp. Subjects DOJ deferral of authority to U.S. Department of Labor; similar strikes in Utah and Arizona. Begins at 0616.
  - [Leadville, Utah, Smelters Strike] Casefile 16-67, 1917; 21 (Reel 7)
    June 25-July 12, 1917. 6pp. Subjects: DOJ deferral of authority to U.S Department of Labor; request for use of federal troops. Begins at 0621.
  - [Hoboken. New Jersey, Dock Strike] Casefile 16-69, 1917; 22 (Reel 7)
    July 3. 1917. 5pp. Subjects: DOJ deferral of authority over strike at the Consolidated Iron Works shipbuilding plant with wartime government contacts; U.S. Board of Mediation and Conciliation attempts to arbitrate dispute. Begins at 0627.
  - [Butte, Montana, Copper Miners Strike] Casefile 16-71, 1917-1920; 23 (Reel 7)
    July 3, 1917-May 21, 1920. 17pp. Subjects: Protests against killing of strikers by local authorities; protests against wartime IWW strikes; Military Intelligence Division reports on situation; U.S. Attorney Burton K. Wheeler's correspondence regarding situation; requests for federal intervention in strike. Begins at 0632.
  - [West Virginia Coal Miners Strike] Casefile 16-72, 1917-1921; 24 (Reel 7)
    April 24, 1917-May 23, 1921. 40pp. Subjects: Affidavits regarding mob violence and intimidation; speeches delivered by UMWA organizers Mary "Mother" Jones and others at Thayer, West Virginia. Begins at 0649.
  - [Birmingham, Alabama, Miners Strike] Casefile 16-75, 1917-1920; 25 (Reel 7)
    August 6, 1917-December 4, 1920. 13pp. Subjects: Bureau of Investigation reports on UMWA strike and coal production in Alabama; anti-union policies of company stores; local officials suppot for mine owners; UMWA contact negotiators. Begins at 0689.
  - [L. Wolff Manufacturing Company Strike, Chicago, Illinois] Casefile 16-76, 1917; 26 (Reel 7)
    July 30-Septembe 3, 1917. 39pp. Subjects: Mob violence and intimidation; alleged IWW involvement in strike of the AFL Foundry Workers' Union; immigrant labor; Illinois State Federation of Labor protests against the Bureau of Investigation activities in Illinois; no appointment of owners of firm as Deputy U.S. Marshals. Begins at 0702.
  - [Boston and Maine Railroad Strike] Casefile 16-77, 1917-1919; 27 (Reel 7)
    September 44, 1917-Decembe 7, 1919. 28pp. Subjects: Arbitration of wartime strikes; AFL Railroad Employees Division; Massachusetts Committee on Public Safety. Begins at 0741.
  - [Yakima, Washington, Lumber and Construction Strike] Casefile 16-79, 1917; 28 (Reel 7)
    August 23-Novembe 8, 1917. 11pp. Subjects: Alleged IWW involvement in strike and U.S. Reclamation Service Camp near Yakima; general strikes of lumber and construction workers on the Pacific Northwest; grand jury investigations. Begins at 0769.
  - [Chattanooga, Tennessee, Street Railway Strike] Casefile 16-80, 1917; 29 (Reel 7)
    September 24-November 10, 1917. 158pp. Subjects: Alleged IWW involvement in strike; Chattanooga Railway and Light Company employment of secret operatives and strikebreakers; Amalgamated Association of Street and Electric Railway Employees of America Union organization; open shop versus closed shop issues; mob violence and intimidation; use of federal troops; use of injunctions in labor disputes; pro-German matters; investigation of federal cases against William D. Haywood, Raymond S. Fanning, and others; requests for federal intervention in strike due to interference with interstate commerce and obstruction of U.S. mails; U.S. Department of Labor arbitration efforts. Begins at 0780.
- Casefile 16-82 through 16-116 (Reel 8)
  - [Fort Smith, Arkansas, General Strike and Telephone Strike] Casefile 16-82, 1917; 1 (Reel 8)
    September 30 - December 12, 1917. 23pp. Subjects: Strike of female telephone operators at Southwestern Bell Telephone Company; sympathy strikes by all organized trades in the area; protests against company efforts to obtain injunctions and U.S. Marshal deputies to guard property; Samuel Gompers' letters to Attorney General Thomas W. Gregory concerning strike and use of federal troops in wartime strikes. Begins at 0000.
  - [Boeing Aircraft Company Strike, Seattle, Washington] Casefile 16-82-1, 1941; 2 (Reel 8)
    March 9 - November 17, 1941. 44pp. Subjects: DOJ investigation of subversive elements and slowdown of production in defense industries; UAW efforts to organize Boeing workers and competition with AFL International Association of Machinists; J. Edgar Hoover FBI memoranda concerning Communist activities, proposed surveillance of Wyndham Mortimer, and employment of special agent. Begins 0023.
  - [Collinsville, Illinois, Smelter Workers Strike] Casefile 16-83, 1917-1918; 3 (Reel 8)
    October 10, 1917-Octobe 21, 1918. 29pp. Subjects: DIJ policy concerning the appearance of U.S. Attorneys in labor litigations; contempt of court proceedings against local officials of the IUMMSW for violation of injunction protecting operations of the St. Louis Smelting and Refining Company; Illinois State Federation of Labor protests against alleged anti-union bias of U.S. Attorney; DOJ deferral of authority to the Council of National Defense and the U.S. Department of Labor; company use of black strikebreakers in outskirts of East St. Louis following race riots; wartime effort to avert labor disputes. Begins at 0067.
  - [Allis-Chalmers Manufacturing Company Strike, West Allis, Wisconsin] Casefile 16-85-1, 1941; 4 (Reel 8)